<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<sect1 id="midi-intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
		The Midi Kit is the API that implements support for generating, processing, and 
		playing music in MIDI format. <ulink url="http://www.midi.org/">MIDI</ulink>, which 
		stands for 'Musical Instrument Digital Interface', is a well-established 
		standard for representing and communicating musical data. 
	</para>

	<para>
		The BeOS comes with two different, but compatible Midi Kits. This documentation 
		focuses on the "new" Midi Kit, or midi2 as we like to call it, that was 
		introduced with BeOS R5. The old kit, which we'll refer to as midi1, is more 
		complete than the new kit, but less powerful.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		Both kits let you create so-called MIDI endpoints, but the endpoints from midi1 
		cannot be shared between different applications. The midi2 kit solves that 
		problem, but unlike midi1 it does not include a General MIDI softsynth, nor 
		does it have a facility for reading and playing Standard MIDI Files. Don't 
		worry: both kits are compatible and you can mix-and-match them in your 
		applications.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		The main differences between the two kits:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Instead of one <classname>BMidi</classname> object that both produces and consumes events, we have 
				<classname>BMidiProducer</classname> and <classname>BMidiConsumer</classname>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Applications are capable of sharing MIDI producers and consumers with other 
				applications via the centralized Midi Roster.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Physical MIDI ports are now sharable without apps "stealing" events from each 
				other.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Applications can now send/receive raw MIDI byte streams (useful if an 
				application has its own MIDI parser/engine).</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Channels are numbered 0..15, not 1..16</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Timing is now specified in microseconds instead of milliseconds.</para></listitem>	
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
</sect1>
