<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd" [

]>

<sect1 id="midi1">
	<title>The Old Midi 1 Kit</title>
	<para>
	The old Midi Kit, or midi1 for short, goes all the way back to DR8, when the 
	BeOS only ran on BeBoxen. Fortunately for us, it is pretty well documented:
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><ulink url="http://bang.dhs.org/be/bebook/The%20Midi%20Kit/index.html">Midi 
			Kit chapter in the online Be Book</ulink></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><ulink url="http://web.archive.org/web/20010618100542/www-classic.be.com/developers/developer_library/midi_kit.html">Midi 
		Kit section of the old Be Developer Library</ulink></para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 1, Issue 49 - Introduces the MIDI synth</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 1, Issue 52 - Follow-up on issue 49</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 1, Issue 91 - How to use BSynth</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 1, Issue 102 - Axe sample code</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 1, Issue 104 - How to use BMidiPort</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 2, Issue 23 - EdMidi sample code</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 2, Issue 37 - How to use the MIDI synth</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Be Newsletter Volume 3, Issue 37 - Whistle sample code</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>
	
	<para>
	To summarize, there are four basic MIDI classes:
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><classname>BMidi</classname> is the base class for most other classes from the Midi Kit.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><classname>BMidiPort</classname> can talk to a MIDI hardware port.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><classname>BMidiStore</classname> can read, write, and perform Standard MIDI files.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><classname>BMidiText</classname> is a debugging aid that dumps MIDI messages to <function>stdout</function></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The following classes let you use the Midi Kit's General MIDI synthesizer:
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para><classname>BSynth</classname> controls the synthesizer.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><classname>BMidiSynth</classname> connects a <classname>BMidi</classname> object to the synth.</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><classname>BMidiSynthFile</classname> connects a MIDI file to the synth</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para><classname>BSamples</classname> lets you access the synth's sound data stream</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist></para>
		
	<para>	
	To make MIDI data stream through your application, you create a "network" of 
	BMidi-derived objects that send and receive MIDI messages.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	The old Midi Kit is slowly fading into obscurity. You may want to use the
	<link linkend="midi2">MIDI 2 Kit</link> instead. Also note that the Haiku implementation
	of the kit sometimes behaves differently than the one from BeOS R5 or what
	the BeBook says, but usually for the better ;-)
	</para>
	
	<para>
	Especially the synth classes are not completely functional, but enough to
	play back General MIDI tunes. They should be backwards compatible with the
	majority of BeOS MIDI applications. Not all methods of BSynth, BMidiSynth,
	and BMidiSynthFile are implemented because some of them are rather obscure. 
	BSamples is a complete no-op; in other words, with the Haiku Midi Kit 
	you cannot push waveform data into the output stream of the softsynth.
	</para>
</sect1>
