<driver id="driver/@@DRVNAME@@">
 <name>@@DRVNAME@@</name>
 <url>http://gimp-print.sourceforge.net/</url>
 <execution>
  <filter />
  <prototype>gs -q -dPARANOIDSAFER -dNOPAUSE -dBATCH -sDEVICE=ijs -sIjsServer=ijsgutenprint.@@STPREL@@ -dIjsUseOutputFD%A -sIjsParams=&quot;@@REMAP@@STP_VERSION=@@STPVER@@,%B&quot;%Z -sOutputFile=- -</prototype>
 </execution>
 <comments>
  <en>

    &lt;b&gt;This page provides data for the IJS driver of Gutenprint
    5.0.  If you are using a Gimp-Print 4.2 release (e. g. 4.2.7),
    driver of the Gimp-Print 4.2.x series, please visit the
    &quot;&lt;a
    href=&quot;show_driver.cgi?driver=gimp-print-ijs&quot;&gt;gimp-print-ijs&lt;/a&gt;&quot;
    page, and if you are using Gimp-Print 4.0.x, go to the &quot;&lt;a
    href=&quot;show_driver.cgi?driver=stp&quot;&gt;stp&lt;/a&gt;&quot;
    page.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;p&gt;

    Gutenprint supports a wide variety of Epson Stylus, HP DeskJet,
    LaserJet, Canon BubbleJet, Lexmark inkjet printers, with the
    primary goal being uncompromising quality.  Epson Stylus printers
    in particular are supported in all resolutions and modes, and many
    models are capable of producing prints that rival photographic
    prints in quality.  This package also offers much faster printing
    for high quality text and presentation graphics when
    required.&lt;p&gt;

    The execution information currently here corresponds to driver
    version @@STPVER@@. If you use another version, use the Foomatic
    data which comes with the Gutenprint package.&lt;p&gt;

    Note that the Foomatic datafiles provided here are only for the
    IJS driver of Gutenprint. For the native CUPS driver there
    are special PPD files provided by the Gutenprint package.&lt;p&gt;

    This driver is built as an IJS driver, which does not require
    recompiling Ghostscript.  It requires an IJS enabled GhostScript
    (GNU GhostScript 6.53 or newer, APFL GhostScript 7.04 or
    newer).&lt;p&gt;

  </en>
 </comments>
 @@STPRINTERS@@
</driver>
